let's start with 30 breaths okay 30 30
breath try to get settle High venerable
feel nice to have
you 30 breaths concentrate on the exhale
which nostril you're going to use
yeah inhale left exhale right here we go
where if your nose is stuffed up
magic okay
so the first uh
of the silky number gay
the first of the eight overpowerings
I'd like you to just
picture
the color red in your mind
so it's
just a color
and get used to seeing red
color with your eyes closed
it takes some practice
and that's where you're going to start
your meditation
if you're gonna emanate something red
you're going to have to be able to pick
your red in your mind
let's turn that to Yellow
so picture yellow color in your mind
your mind is full of yellow color
now let's do a white color
so picture a white color in your mind
now we'll do some shapes and I'd like
you to start there's a big mountain
it's the highest mountain
on the diamond mountain property
and it's right behind the temple
it's called McCullough Peak from the
first director here
and the person who
signed it
paperwork to create diamond mountain
with name Winston McCullough so imagine
that mountain
behind us
and I want you to shrink it
and put it at the center of your mind
so maybe it's only one inch high
take that huge mountain which is I think
over 5 000 feet it's about
2 000 meters
shrink it
to a half inch in your mind
bringing inside your mind and shrink it
now I'd like you to take that little
Mount McCullough in
move it out of your mind
into your hand
and it's still tiny it fits in the palm
of your hands in the palm of your head
Imagine That Mountain has gone out of
your mind
out of the center of your mind
and now it's sitting in the palm of your
head the whole Mountain
come on
now I'd like you to in the center of
your mind
place a single hair from your head
so imagine one single hair
from your head
is in the middle of your mind you are
focusing on
one single hair standing up
now send that single hair outside
and put it behind the temple at Diamond
Mountain where the mountain used to be
now there's a single hair
from your head
the same size as the mountain
behind the temple here at the end of the
valley
a single hair
two thousand meters high
and imagine one of those beautiful
diamond mountain puffy white clouds
the blue sky
over the hair okay
okay there's a large
White
sloppy
crown
bring the cloud into the center of your
mind shrink it
to about one inch like
one or two centimeters
bring it into the middle of your mind
cloud
huge cloud
now dissolve your whole body into that
cloud
so it used to be the cloud was in the
middle of your mind
and now your whole body dissolves into
the cloud and there's just a tiny cloud
but it's you
now you don't look like a human anymore
you look like a club
didn't picture the heart health
a vast iron floor
red hot
and real people naked
running
across the
Aaron
red hot iron screaming in pain
quickly
bring the cloud
bring yourself
to the top of that chamber
and quickly start to send down a
nice
Cool Rain
on those beings the iron floor
of the hot house starts to
cool down
the red color of the floor
starts to fade
the beings there they can stop they
don't have to keep running
the rain is very gentle
very cool you are each drop
each job is you
you are the cloud
and you are each raindrop dropping
and these people are looking up
with great
relief and smile on their faces and
they're reaching out
and you are
dropping into their palm of their hands
you are dropping on their head
you are dropping covering their body
with cool
Pleasant
clean
Rainwater
and they're just really happy
then you decide to become a beautiful
house where they can stay personally
I kind of like
diamond mountain retreat Retreat cabin
but a little bit
bigger a little bit
like
not fancy but comfortable and beautiful
and become a host because now they need
a place to stay
and so in the hell Realms I kind of see
the beautiful green grass
these beautiful little white cottages
and the hell beings are
really happy and they're walking into
the door of these cottages and
and furnished the cottage with your body
I'm a couch
I'm a chair
I'm a kitchen table
and I am clothing
and now they have these beautiful soft
clothing whatever is your favorite
clothing
you can become
that clothing in my hot hell
all the hell beings get really nice
cotton Cowboy shirts
they feel very comfortable
and they're starting to sit down on the
furniture
you are the couch
you are their cloth
then you can become a teacher
uh Drama teacher walks in maybe just
looks like a friend
walks into the
to the house
sits down
in a chair in the living room starts to
tell them about
maybe teaching them Thunderman
and talking to them about Tomlin
you are the couch
you are the house
you are the sky in the clouds outside
you are the
friend just a normal friend teaching
them
then imagine those hell round beings
they start to
cross their legs and go into meditation
they start doing
timeline meditation themselves
and then they become a Buddha
so on you
the couch
in you the house
under you the sky and the clouds
these hell beings in these nice clothes
that are
you have become a Buddha
by doing the tongue land that you taught
them
and just enjoy the whole scene and enjoy
being in the house
enjoy being the coach
enjoy being the nice clothes
enjoy teaching them
and enjoyed the Buddhists that they have
become
in what used to be a hot hill
then you can put that whole
scene shrink it back
bring it back to your mind you can bring
it back to your heart
it's a whole hot hell the whole Sky the
all the clouds
beautiful houses
the furniture
they all shrink
to a DOT
at your heart it's only the size of a
piece of sand
and it's become a Buddha Paradise
deep in your heart
the size of a piece of sand
then you can open your eyes
take a stretch
any questions or comments you guys have
somebody throw a box around Haggerty
um
so we took the mountain and brought it
into our mind and shrank it and then we
took that hair
yeah
and put it out there yeah and then what
was the significance of that what was
the significance of our hair being in
places just to get used to
uh in this special meditation called
silky number overpowering meditation
you are
showing that you have control over the
size of things
so you're able to take a mountain
there's a beautiful
Hendrix song which I'm not allowed to
play
when I'm standing next to a mountain
I chop it down with the edge of my head
so it seemed like he's just standing
next to the mountain
knock the top of the mountain off he
crushes it and he creates an island of
sand
in this song What is that called Booty
Talk
so anyway it's to get used to
controlling the size and the colors of
things
four for the colors and four for
basically the size adjustments
[Music]
and then that's your palette
and from there you can emanate things
first you have to control colors and
shapes and sizes
other question come in
wait you need a box I have four
questions
four pay extra
so this is the full meditation I mean on
on giving to the
Haram uh
and what we did now this is the
meditation we're supposed to do yeah
start with the colors and
do all the reals
and do all the rounds okay animal realm
the pray the realm the human realm okay
um another question a long line of uh of
ourselves about ourselves yeah good and
you said the future me do it on the
future uh what about uh if I have a
problem right now how do I do that
that's fine yeah
also
uh there's a debate about
the patio to it oh okay like uh how much
can you affect the past that's another
question okay another question is um
when I take that the pain of others when
I do Tomlin I don't feel nervous uh is
it a bad sign like because I know I
won't be damaged of of that of taking
that so I I don't feel scared so I'm
like yeah that's fine that's fine like
you understand it so well you don't feel
scared yeah yeah okay and I had a in a I
had a weird uh conversation with
somebody
uh here
and they said uh
I used to do uh their massage therapist
and they said uh I never do people who
are hurting real bad
and I'm like I thought that's what
massage therapist did you know and they
said no no I don't want the bad luck
of massaging a person who has a like
cancer or something you know I don't
want
cancer to come through my hands and
and make me sick or something so they
said I always make sure that
the person I'm giving a massage is
healthy and I thought that was the
stupidest thing I ever heard uh so well
I heard a lot of stupid things actually
but that's pretty bad so yeah uh there's
this
there's this feeling that uh if I take
someone's if I really take someone's
emotional pain for example it might
disturb my mind
but actually the decision to take it has
the opposite effect
so you're right
you don't have to be scared okay and
another question
um can you plant seeds Karma of taking
your own uh pain I mean Karma usually
you you plant seeds by doing that
something to towards other person so can
we plant karma when we do stuff for us
like doing things that's a really good
question can you commit Karma on
yourself I think so but um yeah it is
you can and it's a good question it's a
really good question
and my teacher used to insist that uh
my teacher constantly said
uh how many people does the bodhisattva
work for
and then you say
all living beings do you know there's a
joke in the monastery
we all get assigned to the kitchen I
spend eight years in the kitchen washing
dishes mostly and uh you know and
there's a joke in the monastery if if
someone does a lousy job and the dishes
are dirty
after they clean them they say dollar
Pinscher
it means he washed the dishes for all
living beings
and it means uh for all living beings
has become a
cliche
in the monastery oh everybody's doing
everything for all living beings oh I
guess you wash those dishes following
beans they're really filthy you know it
means that you don't even think about it
and and and my teacher kept saying uh
don't forget you're working for all
living beings and and then this
intense moment I
mean I remember
uh
we were
we were at Princeton
and uh
and he was asking me these questions
about all living things and uh a
lawnmower came by outside you know you
know somebody was mowing the lawn and he
said
is that all living beings
yeah that's one of all living beings the
guy mowing the lawn is one of all living
things and then very quickly he said are
you one of all living things so he
trigged me he said is the guy mowing the
lawn outside we couldn't see him we
could just hear it
and I said yeah he's honoring me and
then quickly my teacher said are you all
living are you are you one of them and I
said well I didn't think about it
but I guess I am and then he says well
then you have to be nice to yourself
also
and he he trapped me you know with the
lawnmower
I remember 1975.
throughout me
December uh like that you know so yeah
you are one of all
get good seats by being nice to yourself
because
you know
Stanley
somebody you know
[Music]
yeah
say it and say it into the blue box the
definition of comma is the movement of
your mind and what it triggers yeah yeah
so uh
it is karma
it's not Karma because somebody somebody
else is karma because you wanted to help
them
that makes it coming
that makes it a seat
okay uh nothing another question anybody
wait you were gonna ask me questions
about this meditation
Jack's here Jack
I just had a technical question about
can you change this to a like a banana
milkshake
never mind
um when we're visualizing the colors and
[Music]
do we when you say bring it into the
mind are you
are you about
we're visualizing the color in our
in our heart or
somewhere else in the body
because I because I grew up in the West
uh because from my whole childhood I was
told my
personally when I do it I
but I technically it's in your heart you
know
um there's a problem there's a potential
problem
of doing these meditations at your heart
chakra it's a very sensitive chakra and
oftentimes they will say don't mess with
your heart chakra keep things out of
your heart chakra because you can get
nervous uh it can make you nervous
and it can make you shaky and so if that
happens
I mean personally I use my head
but uh they say if you're having a shaky
day do it at your navel chakra move it
down to your navel chakra so
you know two two fingers below or four
fingers below your navel
inside and then background is very
grounding so if you're having a
if you're in Retreat for two days or a
thousand days
and you start getting Lungi which means
you start getting nervous
because you're meditating too much to
keep things down in your navel chakra in
uh did you guys have trouble visualizing
just swatches of color
I mean I had trouble with it
it kept turning gray
I don't know
so I I think we need to practice
I think if you practice I think that's
why Lord Buddha
there's a list of like 20 uh drawings
that he wanted in the monastery
and there's a location for each drawing
like the debate ground wall has to have
a certain drawing
and the side of the monks
room has to have those
those swatches of color just swatches of
color and then you have to get used to
closing your eyes and seeing the colors
because you need to master colors to
emanate
although I saw your animations are going
to be Gray
you guys
UCS to box
questions Wow first question is about
about when you when you imagine the
color so you mentioned about the watches
by in the meditation you just let us we
just think about the color right yeah in
in English it's called Swatch or Swatch
it means a big piece
a bit of blue like you painted the wall
like you painted
two meters
uh blue and you're just staring in then
in this code shall we just think of the
color or if we use some format of color
to help for example when you think of
red then I I would think of the red rope
because that was
doing a flower arrangement before that
and I think of railroad's first button
later I make the rows bigger so I just
focus on the red that's it yeah that's
it working yeah that's a good system uh
I personally have trouble
uh thinking of Red without a shape
I need a square and then I paint the
whole Square red and then I can do it
you know so I think you could start like
that I'll start with a red car or a red
house or and then go close and just have
red like zoom in yeah zoom in zoom zoom
zoom in just quick quick question second
I just want to confirm that in this
meditation we imagine that we we play
with the color and shape and the size
and then in the end you guide us to
imagine that we are the chair we are the
house we are the uh we are the data we
have the Buddha and by Imagine This are
we planting the sea so we could have the
emanation capacity that's why we're
doing it okay good thank you
uh there's four bodies of a Buddha right
in the expanded explanation
and one of them is called chuku
which means emanation
look at that
to emanate as a person for example
you're going to need all kinds of colors
all different shapes
otherwise you're gonna be flat with no
ears no you have to be good at shapes
and stomach
so many other questions
I believe you said that on the
wall hanging I'm Lord with the headset
there should be five colors but then I
think you said that there's four colors
in the meditation is there a missing I'm
gonna look it up hang on this is in
Masters against book which is a really
amazing book
I'll give you the vinaya Sutra
okay that's the source
[Music]
hmm
yeah so here's the vanilla Sutra okay
uh into gang's book
s yeah
[Music]
foreign
Lord Buddha says
I want
means the entryway in the in the
entryway of the Temple there should be a
salsara chakra Ganda Pancha
should have five parts
of the five Realms okay okay in the
belly by the way
the the part before that
says which means in the entryway which
is the
durare
yeah
yeah so Russian is normally closer
and where
yaksha
demon monster the guy who's holding the
Wheel of Life
he's called yaksha chitran chitranam uh
chitra here means various
but it refers to a painter so the word
for a painter in Sanskrit is the many
color guy
okay
he should be holding a vaja
he should be me
put him at the door that's vinaya Sutra
verse
17th section
go to verse 210 go backwards you ready
and this is all from uh gang's amazing
book
uh
you should paint
colors Crystal colors on the wall
of the Monk's quarters Nila niladi ADI
means Etc
Nila
uh sapphire blue the wording sounds good
for
sapphires Indonesia
Sydney yeah
so he says on the on the monks quarter
walls who asked me the question
I want blue
Etc now
so I went and got a commentary for you
uh which John Brady discovered
and it's extremely valuable
it's the greatest commentary ever done
on vinaya
volumes it's 2 000 Pages roughly eight
thousand sixteen thousand pages in
English
he says
I want to see blue
okay he says I want to see limbo blue
I want to see serpo yellow
and I want to see La SOPA
Etc
thanks a lot
uh
yeah but he does uh let me get it for
you
any quotes
yeah now here is blue yellow red and
white
that's um Guna prabhas own commentary to
himself
the guy who wrote the vinaya Sutra
Sutra said when I said blue Etc I meant
yellow red and white it's a blue yellow
that's the tradition for painting the
wall
and and supposedly that's enough colors
to build everything up
any other question one more of course
how about two more questions
how long should we be able to hold the
object for is there a recommended time
for example if I can imagine the
mountain shrinking and expanding quickly
should I still prolong it or is yeah if
you notice that meditation normally
myself
when I'm doing a meditation that has
Progressive elements I will spend five I
time it in breath
I do five to ten breaths 10 breaths is
normal for me if I'm doing a meditation
where I have to do
changing scenes I like to do 10 breaths
so I got used to the perfect 10 many
years ago
it's kind of natural for me
and then I I hold it for for 10 breaths
and then I move to the next scene if you
feel yourself getting sleepy
move it faster
if you feel yourself getting distracted
to slow down
and take 20 breaths on each step so it's
a it's a balance you have to keep things
moving or else your mind will get bored
but if you move them too fast you'll
start thinking about lunch
is what I'm doing right now I'm okay
thank you my question is coming back to
the visualizations uh so when we are
visualizing the house the people running
those beings I understand that we have
to make it as precise as we can but
sometimes I cannot do it I just
see some see some just uh like objects
or something
and my question is what seeds we can
plan to make those
visualizations as clear or as precise as
we can yeah good good so she said
I know I'm supposed to be like a luxury
apartment in the Hill Road
but I have sometimes
I have trouble getting all the details
I just kind of be on luxury apartment
and move on
and
that's okay and then she asked
a much more intelligent part of her
question was what's the seeds
to be able to
to fill in the luxury apartment with all
the right stuff
what are the seats to do that
and we've been spending a lot of time in
Japan recently
and they were deeply affected by uh Tom
Dynasty China so 1 400 years ago they
were
deeply affected by
truly classical Chinese culture in
and and they developed this kind of uh
so we were
we were negotiating on a building
for the University
and buying a building in Japan is not an
easy thing and negotiating with Japanese
is not an easy thing uh
it's a very rude
right Tim
uh
to uh rush things
and so you know we've been going there
month after month and having tea
together
and taking a long time on the T
and not mentioning why we're there and
uh
but the whole Tea Ceremony has to be
very elegant and you focus on it
everything's clean everything has a
everything is tidy and neat and Japan in
general
is kind of a Tom Dynasty mirror
especially Kyoto when you get out of
Tokyo outside of Tokyo
you have this Elegance it's an Elegance
and it's hard for an American it's
really difficult for an American because
we're messy and uh we like when we go
home I don't know about you guys Tim
throw my clothes on the floor and get to
bed you know and maybe I pick them up
tomorrow and maybe I don't you know and
in Japan you would
mindfully there's this whole zen garden
thing you rake the white gravel and
and you try to do everything mindfully
and you serve the team mind to me
do the Ikebana flower arrangements
mindfully
and I I think sometimes it can be too
much
but
when you're there and you see the effect
of that mindset it's kind of elegant
and I think if you don't get too crazy
about it
if you are careful
to make your
surroundings elegant
uh and I like the word elegant I don't
mean just fold your clothes I mean
think about it and fold them sweetly and
and put them in a nice what's that
lady's name who does the boxes and stuff
what's your name Marie
you heard the the scandal with Marie
kondo
she uh
she got famous for telling people to
clean up their houses
and I I saw her videos and I tried and
uh
Anjali helped me we got everything in
boxes right and uh we even have a book
that tells you which box your junk is in
and um
and then uh recently so she got famous
she got rich she had a she bought a
house and she got married and she had
kids when she got to her third kid she
made a public announcement that if
you've had if you have three or more
kids forget my system
and then there's all these ladies who
have three kids 10 years ago
and then they're really pissed off that
they were trying to put everything in
boxes and met his three kids and then
she told them 10 years later it's not
possible with three kids
so why am I saying that there's still
this Japanese Sensibility
of uh of being mindful of small things
like how you pour the tea and how you
put things away in
in the condition of your bedroom for
example like you can
the way I make a bed is that going you
know and they would smooth it out and
and make it and I think that kind of uh
care
everyday care which is a kind of Somali
is I think it's a very good thing I I
don't
I'm not very good at it but I when I am
I think it plants the seeds to be able
to do the details in the luxury
apartment in the hell rooms but
I think that kind of samadhi about
how you keep your house how you keep
your schedule
uh is uh is the cause for the detail in
the hell room
and I think that part of Japanese
culture is really beautiful
started to do a little bit of it but not
much
uh
my computer blew up again so let's have
one more question
okay
okay so this is a question from from
Julieta Julieta I'm not sure where
they're from
um
what happens if if I hear some
or see some bad news something bad
happening
can I use this disturbing image that I
have already seen in my imagination or
meditation to turn it into a Buddha
Paradise
yeah I I get that
for me
it's uh I never watched the news in my
whole life and I never had a television
my whole life
and then during the last elections in
the United States
to know what was going on
and uh
and I got this bad habit now and I do
look at the news every day though
and it's a bad I think it's a bad habit
I I think you should be aware
of what news is happening in the world
generally
but I don't think you have to read the
same news four or five times
and um
that's what has become for me sometimes
so uh
I think uh
you see disturbing images in the news
they will show images of war or things
like that and it's it's very disturbing
for your money
and can you use it
can it become useful
we translated their karma debanga
which is a book that we finished last
year
and it's called all the kinds of karma
and it's a good book it's a Sutra
so somebody asked Lord Buddha
could you just give us a list of the
basic types of karma that exist
and he gave a long teaching and he
outlined all the possible
basically the the grand outline of all
the kinds of karma we translated the
title as all the kinds of karma
and we found it carved into a pyramid
in Indonesia
and then this lady named Gina Rivera
who's a genius from Guadalajara
oh
[Applause]
she did all the drawings it took about a
year and a half I think
it was hard
and it's a beautiful beautiful book okay
there's an interesting
teaching in that book and there's a
drawing of it
of uh allowing children to watch
violence
[Music]
talking about the karma
of watching violence like my wife
Veronica who's coming on Thursday but
here
Thursday and Friday
um she will not watch violence like I
kind of like war movies I don't know
because I like to see what's his name
Brad Pitt Drive the tank impossibly over
12 more Mountains and you know I enjoy
that kind of thing but she just she just
walks out
and she says I don't want that image in
my head you know
let's walk out so I think um
I think there's
according to the karma of ibanga you you
want to avoid those images
and then there there it becomes a skill
monks are supposed to develop okay
okay and I had to use it in New York for
19 years
uh we're supposed to keep our eyes down
uh so I I would come into the Port
Authority Bus Terminal every day
like about a million people coming
through that terminal
every day
and I'm supposed to keep my eyes down
and still make it to the right Subway
you know and I'm not supposed to look at
the cute ladies and stuff like that you
know I'm supposed to keep my eyes down
and so there's a monks practice
to to be able to move your eyes within
half a look
okay within half a look do you see the
lady and you and you get a what do you
call it
it becomes a instinct
you just a re you just look down
and so you you never see the whole image
you catch a glimpse and then you look
down
now I think we could do that for images
of violence
okay so if you rather than eating it up
like
you know learn this uh monastic skill
of turning your eyes away quickly okay
if you dwell on the image
it will get planted
if you can if you can learn to control
your eyes
and look away
as an as a real instinctively
those images won't be burned into your
mind
can you use an image like that uh it's
fully yeah
like uh there's many examples of that
you can imagine that you are throwing a
bomb
at your selfishness or something you
know
you know you did a Hypersonic missile to
your
to your irritation with your friend
you can do stuff you can use them you
can use those images but in general
wouldn't it be better to floor throw
flowers at your enemies
supersonic